Guide to the Patrick James Nicholson research for Mr. Jim: The Biography of James Smither Abercrombie, 1846-1982 MS 391
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Patrick James Nicholson research for Mr. Jim: The Biography of James Smither Abercrombie
1846-1982
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Nicholson, Patrick James
MS 391
0.75 Linear Feet (1 box)
This collection is composed of research materials and manuscripts of Patrick J. Nicholson for his book Mr. Jim: The Biography of James Smither Abercrombie. Included are photocopies of various articles about J.S. Abercrombie, correspondence concerning Nicholson's research, notes, and typed copies of the manuscript.
Biographical / Historical
Patrick James Nicholson is the author of Mr. Jim: The Biography of James Smither Abercrombie.
Dr. Patrick James Nicholson (1921-1999) is best known as the author of In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston. He received a BA from Rice University in 1942, an MBA from Harvard in 1946, and a Ph.D., from the University of Houston in 1959. Nicholson came to the University of Houston as a lecturer in Management in 1951. He continued until 1956, when he became Executive Director of Development and Assistant to the President. He was named Vice President of University Development in 1957, a position he maintained until his retirement in August of 1981. Honorary positions Nicholson held included Past President of the American College Public Relations Association; Past President of the Houston Council on World Affairs; Past President of the Institute of Ophthalmology, Texas Medical Center; and N.Y. Academy of Sciences. He was a member of Phi Kappa Phi; Phi Eta Sigma; Sigma Xi; and Omicron Delta Kappa. (excerpted from finding aid for Dr. Patrick J. Nicholson Papers at University of Houston, accessed on-line at https://findingaids.lib.uh.edu/repositories/2/resources/171)
Scope and Contents
This collection is composed of research materials and manuscripts of Patrick J. Nicholson for his book Mr. Jim: The Biography of James Smither Abercrombie. Included are photocopies of various articles about J.S. Abercrombie, correspondence concerning Nicholson's research, notes, and typed copies of the manuscript.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Dr. Patrick James Nicholson on September 17, 1985.
Index Terms
Subjects
Authors; Business
Document Types
reports; notes; typescripts; manuscripts (document genre); photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Abercrombie, James Smither
- Series I: Research, Manuscripts, and Reports, 1846-1982; 37950
  - Research Notes, 1982; 37952 (Folder 1)
  - Research Material, correspondence, notes, 1982; 37953 (Folder 2)
  - Typed Manuscript, chapters 1-4, 1982; 37954 (Folder 3)
  - Typed Manuscript, chapters 5-10, 1982; 37955 (Folder 4)
  - Typed Manuscript (copy) with annotations, 1982; 37956 (Folder 5)
  - Typed Manuscript copy, incomplete, 1982; 37957 (Folder 6)
  - Annual reports: Cameron Iron Works; Texas Children's Hospital, St. Luke's Episcopal Hospital, Texas Heart Institute, 1982; 37958 (Folder 7)
  - Walker County, TX research materials: Marriage Records of Walker County, 1846-1880, 1870 Census of Walker County, Texas., 37959 (Folder 8)
  - Research materials: Abercrombie family, 37960 (Folder 9)
  - Research materials: James Elkins, Sr., 37961 (Folder 10)
  - Research materials: misc., 37962 (Folder 11)
- Series II. Photographs, 1983; 37951
  - Photographs, 1983; 37963; Eight colored 3.5X5 photos of a graveyard (Folder 12)